welcome back this is category five
dobrodošli nazad ovo je kategorija pet
technology TV find our website at
Tehnologija TV pronaći našu web stranicu na
category five dot TV joined tonight by
kategorija pet dot TV se pridružio večeras
Shizue Yamaguchi of course sash is here
Shizue Yamaguchi naravno je tu
as well but she zoo was here about a
kao i ona, ali zoološki vrt je bio ovde oko a
year ago and talked to us about them is
prije godinu dana i razgovarali s nama o njima
it Marie Kondo the Mari a condo matter a
to je Marie Kondo , Mari, kondom a
art of tidying up it has certainly had
umetnost pospremanja je svakako imala
an impact on my household the
uticaj na moje domaćinstvo
organization skills of my wife and she's
organizacijske sposobnosti moje supruge i ona
tried to push these these lessons that
pokušali su da ove te lekcije podstaknu
she's learned on me I am okay I'll admit
naučila je o meni da sam dobro, priznajem
it
to
have you ever done a google search about
da li ste ikada napravili google pretraživanje
being disorganized
biti neorganizovan
I have never googled being disorganized
Nikada nisam bio googled da sam neorganizovan
because this changed I figured I was
jer se ovo promenilo, mislio sam da jesam
already real life we have the book my
već u stvarnom životu imamo knjigu svoju
wife even bought the manga version so
žena je čak kupila manga verziju
that so that the kids can read it maybe
da bi deca to mogla da pročitaju
you can also read it okay so this is how
možete ga pročitati u redu tako da je ovo kako
long do I have
dugo imam
we've got about 25 minutes okay so you
imamo oko 25 minuta u redu, tako da
want to quickly recap what is this yeah
hoću da brzo ponovimo šta je ovo da
so last year I came on the show and I
prošle godine sam došao na predstavu i ja
had read this book the marry a condo
je pročitao ovu knjigu o braku sa stanom
it's called the konmari method and the
zove se konmari metoda i
book title is called the life-changing
naslov knjige se naziva promenom života
magic of tidying up and the basic
magija čišćenja i osnovne
proposition of yeah the basic
prijedlog da je osnovni
proposition of this book is that you
prijedlog ove knjige je da ste vi
should get your act together and clean
trebalo bi da se udružite i očistite
your stuff up however in a very specific
Vaše stvari su ipak vrlo specifične
manner so that everything you keep is
tako da sve što držiš jeste
something that you feel a feeling of joy
nešto što osjećate radost
and magic and this feeling of just like
i magije i ovaj osjećaj kao
wow this is the greatest thing ever so
ovo je najveća stvar ikada
you go through the through your shirts
idete kroz kroz košulje
your pants your everything your books
tvoje hlače sve tvoje knjige
your personal belongings everything you
vaše lične stvari sve što vam
own basically you put through that
vlastitu osnovi si stavio kroz to
filter and it's not witchcraft this is
filtrira i to nije Witchcraft je ovo
like
like
I'll go through I've gone through its it
Proći ću kroz to
sounds a little heebie-jeebie when it's
zvuči malo heebie-jeebie kada je
like oh the you know is it magic is
kao što znate da je magija
about joy I go through my cupboard in my
o radosti prolazim kroz ormar u svom
closet and I okay I lost some weight a
ormar i ja sam izgubio malo težine a
year ago
prije godinu
yeah I'm still losing weight and there
Da, još uvek gubim težinu i tamo
are shirts that when I put them on I
to su košulje koje ih stavljam na ja
feel ha ha ha and I feel like I feel
osećam ha ha ha i osećam se kao da se osećam
really disgusted with myself so I'm like
Stvarno se gadim sobom, tako da sam
I need to get rid of these shirts
Moram da se otarasim ovih košulja
because they sparked that feeling yeah
jer su izazvali taj osjećaj
when I put them on and and if they're
kada ih stavim i ako su
the only thing that's clean I will put
jedina stvar koja je čista stavit ću
them on and and so I don't I don't want
na njima i tako ja ne želim
that so get rid of them replenish my
tako da ih se oslobodite popunite moje
well ok robe so it's a very interesting
dobro ok ogrtač tako da je vrlo zanimljivo
it's an interesting topic and I've been
to je zanimljiva tema i ja sam bio
thinking a lot about it since I had the
Razmišljao sam mnogo o tome otkako sam imao
opportunity to actually apply this
mogućnost da se to zaista i primijeni
method to my computer so maybe I'll just
metodu do mog kompjutera pa ću možda samo
get started on that first because this
počnite prvo s tim jer ovo
organization systemization it worked
sistematizacija organizacije je funkcionisala
really well with my computer I do have a
jako dobro sa mojim računalo imam
caveat on the method and I think it's an
upozorite na metodu i mislim da je
important one because it helps me to
važan jer me to pomaže da se
better embrace being disorganized in
Bolje zagrljaj se neorganizirano u
certain aspects of my life and I think
mislim na određene aspekte mog života
it's just an add-on maybe like an
to je samo dodatak možda kao
addendum to the book at the back maybe
dodatak knjizi na poleđini možda
you know like a Asterix being
znate kao Asteriks
disorganized is actually a sign of maybe
neorganizovan je zapravo znak možda
a sign of something else great actually
znak nečeg velikog u stvari
[Laughter]
[Smeh]
so let's go through the process so we'll
pa idemo kroz proces, tako da ćemo
go through this application to my
proći kroz ovu aplikaciju na moj
computer so have you have you taken what
kompjuteru , jesi li uzela šta
you learned and applied those principles
naučili ste i primenili te principe
now to the technology that you use yes
sada na tehnologiju koju koristite da
this specifically something that's
to je nešto posebno
talked about in the book it's not really
govori u knjizi to nije baš
talked about in the book but I know that
o tome sam govorio u knjizi, ali znam to
last year when we spoke about this
prošle godine kada smo razgovarali o ovome
method you asked about you know how does
Metoda koju ste pitali znaju kako to radi
this apply to computers or you know I
ovo se odnosi na računare ili znate ja
think Sasha you actually had a question
Mislim da je Sasha zapravo imala pitanje
about you know would you scan every
znate da biste skenirali svaki
you really loved and then put it onto
ti si stvarno volela i onda je stavila
your computer somewhere and I didn't I
negde kompjuter , a ja nisam
don't know if I had the best answer for
ne znam da li sam imao najbolji odgovor
that however computers are very I mean
međutim, računari su vrlo
they're interesting things I mean they
to su zanimljive stvari koje mislim
have different facets you can put in a
imate različite aspekte koje možete staviti u
million documents into your one terabyte
miliona dokumenata u jedan terabajt
computer I guess right I do have a
kompjuter Pretpostavljam da imam
Windows computer at home and it does
Windows računar kod kuće i on to radi
have that capability and I actually
imam tu sposobnost i ja
would have applied it to my my Windows
bi ga primenio na moj Windows
PC however I really don't have to have
PC ipak ne moram imati
so much space it's just it's so
toliko prostora je samo tako
straightforward you just type whatever I
jednostavno samo tip šta god
need a bigger closet not really well
ne treba mi veći ormar
maybe maybe what may do you think about
možda možda o čemu mislite
doing it on your Mac is it doesn't have
to radi na vašem Mac je nema
as much space um you know what it was I
koliko prostora um znate šta sam ja
just had some free time and I was like
samo imala slobodnog vremena i ja sam bio poput
hey let's just see what happens if I
hej da vidimo šta će se desiti ako ja
organize this in a way that's a little
organizujte ovo na način koji je malo
bit more streamlined okay I can't wait
malo više racionalno u redu ne mogu čekati
to learn this so I'm gonna switch over
da nauče to tako da ću prebacivanje
to your MacBook I'm just so the viewers
na vaš MacBook sam baš kao gledaoci
at home can see what what you're showing
kod kuće možete vidjeti što prikazujete
here yeah
here yeah
all right so say hello to my favorite
sve u redu pa pozdravite moju omiljenu
band member of The Strokes
član grupe The Strokes
Julian Casablancas he's being a little
Julian Casablancas je malo
unfriendly my apologies so this is my
Neprijatno moje izvinjenje tako da je ovo moje
opening screen and usually with max in
otvaranje ekrana i obično sa maks
general they have this doc thing at the
generalno imaju tu dokumentaciju
bottom and what I did was usually
dno i ono što sam uradio je obično
there's the doc has a long line of a
tu je doc ima dugu liniju a
bunch of things that you can keep on
gomila stvari koje možete nastaviti
there but what I did is I minimized it
ali ono što sam uradio je da sam ga minimizirao
to the two things that I need so chrome
dve stvari koje mi trebaju tako hrom
is on there and finder was it finder you
je tamo i tražilo je da te Finder
can't get rid of so the trash crazily I
ne mogu se riješiti tako smeće ludo
actually just went through my trash
zapravo je samo prošao kroz moje smeće
today in preparation for this oh yeah
danas u pripremi za ovo
because obviously you know you want to
jer očigledno znate da to želite
keep your computer apropos you know do
držati tvoj računalo apropos znate uraditi
you know what personal documents showing
znate šta pokazuju lični dokumenti
up so anyway I emptied my trash and
tako da sam ionako ispraznio smeće i
there were 60,000 items
bilo je 60.000 predmeta
Wow that I deleted look you already
Wow da sam vas već izbrisala
decided that this was garbage oh yeah
odlučio sam da je ovo smeće
I'd put it into my trash I've only had
Stavio bih ga u smeće koje sam imao
this computer for a year and I don't
ovog kompjutera godinu dana, a ja ne
know how I had so much damage but I went
znam kako sam imao toliko štete, ali sam otišao
into like okay I can literally open them
u dobro kao da ih mogu bukvalno otvoriti
out my trash right now and there's a
izvuci moje smece sada i tu je
screenshot that's it nice but anyway I
screenshot to je lijepo ali ionako ja
was like 60,000 okay all right so let's
je kao i 60.000 u redu sve u redu pa hajde
begin at the beginning so I decided
početi na početku pa sam odlučio
since finder was there I decided to
Pošto je tražilo tamo, odlučio sam
optimize it so usually and this
optimizirati ga tako obično i ovo
information this this concept transcends
informacije koje ovaj koncept prevazilazi
the MacBook to Linux Windows it doesn't
MacBook za Linux Windows ne
matter what type of computer I use yeah
nije važno koji tip računara koristim da
the concepts that she's who is teaching
koncepte koje ona predaje
us today are hopefully gonna work their
nadamo se da ćemo danas raditi na njihovom
way to my Linux desktop as well yeah so
način da se moje Linux desktop, kao i da tako
I basically just wanted to make my
Zapravo sam samo hteo da napravim svoj
computer mine how I use it what I use
kompjuterska mina kako je koristim ono što koristim
the most and so what I did is I just
najviše što sam uradio je samo
minimized minimize minimize and I
minimizirano minimiziranje i minimiziranje
thought about what elements I use the
razmišljala o elementima koje koristim
most so I just made it the most useful
najviše sam ga učinio najkorisnijim
computer for me and the benefits in this
kompjuter za mene i koristi od toga
I'll just say this up front mmm my
Reći ću samo ovo ispred mene
battery life my battery life my battery
trajanje baterije baterija moj baterija
life is actually improved quite a bit
život je zapravo malo poboljšan
really that's just a subjective thing
to je stvarno subjektivna stvar
but you know how you always it because
ali znate kako uvek to radite
of programs that are not running in the
programa koji se ne izvode u
background is but I feel like optimizing
pozadina je, ali mi se sviđa optimizacija
your usage of it somehow I don't and it
Vaše korišćenje nekako ne i to
definitely wasn't because of all of the
definitivno nije bilo zbog svih
items that I had on it because I just
stvari koje sam imao na sebi, jer sam samo
deleted those documents right in the
izbrisao je te dokumente direktno u
trash yeah today so maybe it's
trava da danas tako da je možda
subjective but I really like plugging it
subjektivno, ali stvarno volim da ga uključim
in I just don't do it I don't think I'd
u to jednostavno ne radim, mislim da ne bih
do it as often as I used to and I had
učiniti onoliko često koliko sam nekada i sam imao
had my computer since last June so I
imao sam kompjuter od juna prošle godine, tako da sam
think it's a pretty decent you know
Mislim da je to prilično pristojan znate
comparison right I see things like Skype
poredim pravo Vidim stvari kao što je Skype
on your screen for example yes and Skype
na ekranu, na primer, da i Skype
is not in the dock bar so I presume that
nije na optuženičkoj klupi, bar tako pretpostavljam da
means it's not actually running it's not
znači da zapravo ne radi
which means it's not using battery
što znači da ne koristi bateriju
Yeah right okay so basically what I did
Da, u redu, u osnovi ono što sam uradio
here is I I set it up so that it opens
evo II je podesiti tako da se otvara
up on the applications and I named I
na aplikacijama i ja sam nazvao I
renamed I tried to find a way to put all
Preimenovan Pokušao sam pronaći način da sve stavim
of the most used applications that I use
najčešće korišćenih aplikacija koje koristim
up front and center okay and I really
napred i centar u redu i ja stvarno
tried to minimize as much as possible
pokušao da što je moguće više umanjiti
and I would have put so this is my
i rekao bih da je ovo moje
organizational system so I movie I named
organizacioni sistem, tako da sam film nazvao
one Photoshop I named one one okay so is
jedan Photoshop koji sam imenovao jedan je u redu
this just so that they'll organize
ovo samo tako da će oni organizirati
themselves alphabetically on your screen
na vašem ekranu
so that they'll show up first so the
tako da će se pojaviti na prvoj tako da
first thing that happens when I click on
Prva stvar koja se događa kada sam kliknite na
applications is I'll see one one one one
aplikacija je vidim jednu
on one and it was an airy it's binary
na jednom i to je bilo prozračno binarno
[Laughter]
[Smeh]
done like a one zero one two that have
učinjeno kao jedna nula dvije
been a little fun alternate a little bit
bilo je malo zabave alternativno malo
yeah yeah you know what that was that
Da, znate šta je to bilo
was really good and I think I had to
bilo je stvarno dobro i mislim da sam morao
figure out what the system was for max
shvatiti ono što je sistem za max
and how they organized it cuz I think a
i kako su ga organizovali jer ja mislim a
didn't work okay for some reason or one
iz nekog razloga nije dobro funkcionisalo
the ones just worked better so anyway
oni samo radili bolje tako svejedno
those are the four the five most used
to su četiri najčešće korišćena
applications that I do use I would have
aplikacije koje koristim ja bih imao
put so there's iMovie Photoshop word
tako da postoji iMovie Photoshop reč
GarageBand that should probably be
GarageBand to bi trebalo da bude
higher now actually and Skype and System
više sada zapravo i Skype i System
Preferences is where all the magic
Preference su sve magije
happens I would have tried to name that
dogodi bih pokušao nazvati tu
with some one combination to get it up
sa nekom kombinacijom da bi se podigla
front but they wouldn't allow me to
ali nisu mi dozvolili
change that okay so that's one of the
promenite to u redu tako da je to jedan od
maybe faults in the system however it
možda greške u sistemu međutim
might not be a good idea to actually
možda ne bi bila dobra ideja da zapravo
lose track of System Preferences right
Izgubili ste prave sistemske postavke
right you're relying almost exclusively
pravo se oslanjate gotovo isključivo
on the icon itself like the Photoshop
na samoj ikoni kao što je Photoshop
icon is how you recognize that it that I
ikona je kako ti priznati da je to što sam
I or one one is oh yeah for sure for
I ili jedan jedan je oh yeah sigurno za
sure yeah yeah
Sigurno da
but yeah if you can imagine what Apple
ali da, ako možete zamisliti šta je Apple
thinks about when they name when they
razmišlja o tome kada ih zovu kada
allow naming or don't allow naming
dozvolite imenovanje ili ne dozvolite imenovanje
renaming if you were to lose System
preimenovanje ako izgubite Sistem
Preferences somehow you named it like
Preferencije nekako ste ga nazvali
Bing bong bang or something like that
Bing bong prasak ili nešto slično
like right that would not be good
kao da to ne bi bilo dobro
because if you were trying to change
jer ako se pokušavate promijeniti
some kind of setting that was important
neka vrsta postavljanja je bila važna
you would not know where system
ne biste znali gde je sistem
preference was right okay so this is the
preferencija je bila u redu, pa je ovo
thing that I kind of liked I went
stvar koju sam nekako volio da sam otišao
through adjusted the dock you know
kroz prilagođene pristaništa znate
minimized some of this stuff I
minimizirao neke od ovih stvari
experimented with the dock I don't know
eksperimentisao sa dokom koji ne znam
how familiar are you with Max oh well
koliko si ti dobro upoznat sa Max Oh dobro
it's very similar to Linux in that you
veoma je sličan Linuxu u tome
know with Linux like this to me looks
znam da mi Linux izgleda ovako
like met a with with a dock bar okay so
kao što sam upoznao sa barom za pristanište
pretty pretty much the same and it seems
prilično slično i izgleda
very cool do they have so basically the
vrlo cool oni imaju tako u osnovi
dock bar can be minimized it can do this
dock bar mogu svesti na minimum da to može učiniti
I'll show you scale effect genie effect
Pokazaću vam efekat genetskog efekta
if I come out of here
ako izađem odavde
there are many different things you can
postoji mnogo različitih stvari koje možete
do with the dock so you can actually
uradite sa dokom tako da možete
position it in different places oh okay
postavite ga na različitim mjestima oh dobro
so I experimented with that I
tako da sam eksperimentisao s tim
experimented with the size as well I had
eksperimentisao sa veličinom kao i ja
it like this big but that was a little
to je ovako veliko, ali malo
too much what else did I do
previše šta sam još uradio
I tried doing the automatically hide and
Pokušao sam da se automatski sakrijem i
show dock feature as well yeah so this
pokažite i funkciju doka, da, tako da
is a feature and I'll just change the
je funkcija i ja ću samo promijeniti
size of it and make it big so you can
veličinu i učinite je velikom kako biste mogli
kind of see what happens so this allows
vidim šta se dešava tako da to dozvoljava
you to use the full screen and anytime
da koristite ceo ekran i bilo kada
you need it you just mouse over and it
trebaš ga samo mišem i to
like it shows up for you I don't like
kao da ti se to ne sviđa
this and I don't know why but that just
ovo i ne znam zašto, ali to samo
was my preference I personal preference
bila je moja preferencija lična preferencija
because I don't know I can't immediately
jer ne znam odmah
see where it is and it's kind of
vidjeti gdje je to i to je nekako
annoying to have to do two actions
neugodno da moram da uradim dve akcije
instead of just one I just on a Windows
umesto samo jednog na Windowsu
machine there's a Windows button that
mašina postoji dugme za Windows koji
brings up your Start menu is there
otvara vaš Start meni
anything like that on a MacBook that you
bilo šta slično na MacBook-u koji vi
know yeah not really
znam da ne stvarno
no yeah yeah that would be ideal you
ne da da, to bi bilo idealno za vas
could probably search for programs just
verovatno bi mogao samo da traži programe
like you can search for programs just
kao što možete pretraživati ​​samo programe
like you can as well I just fix this
kao što možeš i ja da popravim ovo
back okay so moving on this is actually
nazad u redu, tako da se kreće na ovo zapravo
the one feature that I actually really
jedna stvar koju sam zapravo stvarno
like date and time yeah this is kind of
kao što je datum i vreme
a feature that's just kind of fun I
osobina koja je samo zabavna
think so every quarter hour you can
mislim da svaki sat i po možete
customize a voice to tell you the time
prilagodite glas koji će vam reći vrijeme
so please hear out there's different
zato vas molim da čujete drugačije
voices you can choose there's Karen
glasovi koje možete izabrati je Karen
or Fiona yeah I asked my favorite is the
ili Fiona yeah sam pitao moj omiljeni je
youth system voice which is not a very
glas omladinskog sistema koji nije baš
nice or like what's in a name
lepo ili kao što je u imenu
I guess you systems by my voice so it's
Pretpostavljam da sistemima moj glas, tako da je
telling you something it's it's you're
reći ti nešto što je to
hearing a voice
čuti glas
let's hear Karen name is Karen so they
čujemo da je Karen ime Karen i oni
have a natural this is your clock
imati prirodno ovo je tvoj sat
instead of having a clock on the screen
umesto da imate sat na ekranu
well the clocks on the screen but it's
i satovi na ekranu, ali je
it's a bit of a relief because I'm not
to je malo olakšanje jer nisam
always checking the time mm-hmm so when
uvek proveravam vreme mm-hmm tako kada
I'm using my computer I just kind of get
Koristim svoj računar
automatically updated right how much
automatski se ažurira koliko
time has passed yeah and it's not it's
Prošlo je vreme da, i nije to
actually incredibly non intrusive to
u stvari neverovatno nepristojno
have the time just kind of told to you
imao vremena nekako je rekao da te
and I think in general right this seems
i mislim da uopšteno ovo izgleda
to be the direction of IOT s in general
da je pravac IOT e u cjelini
right with like Google home and yeah
sa Googleovom kućom i da
these different devices there's some
postoje različiti uređaji
cookies yeah just easier sorry we're
kolačiće da, lakše mi je žao što smo
talking with Alexa about just
razgovor sa Alexa o pravednom
reminiscing about doll houses and
reminising o kućama za lutke i
cookies all right vea vea name is
kolačići sve je u redu veña veña name je
veena I am an Indian English so the
veena Ja sam indijski engleski tako
organizational kind of process for you
organizacioni proces za vas
has been not just to clean up your
nije bilo samo da se očisti
desktop and things like that but also to
desktop i slične stvari, ali i
customize your computer make it feel
prilagodite računar tako da se oseća
more like hey this is cheezer's computer
više kao hej ovo je cheezer-ov kompjuter
it's meant to work for you yeah it's
to je značilo da radi za vas
very much optimized optimized to what I
veoma optimizovan optimizovan za ono što ja
like cool and I think the aspect that
kao cool i mislim da je aspekt koji
relates to Mary condo is well
odnosi se na Marijin stan
organization as well your desktop looks
organizaciji, kao i desktop izgled
incredibly uncluttered which I love yes
neverovatno neobrezano što volim da
and I and I kind of envy because mine
i ja i ja nekako zavidimo zbog moje
ends up getting filled with icons yeah
završava se ispunjavanjem ikonama da
how about you yeah
Kako o tebi da
I'll tell ya my simple way around it is
Reći ću vam da je to jednostavan način
I just hide my icons you hide your
Samo sakrivam svoje ikone koje sakrivaš
desktop icons yes cuz I like my
desktop ikone da cuz volim svoj
wallpaper right right paperwork is a
tapete desna papirologija je
picture from the balcony where Dave and
slika sa balkona gde Dave i
I had our honeymoon and it's all palm
Imao sam medeni mesec i sve je to dlan
trees in the water and I want to see it
drveće u vodi i želim da je vidim
so I just hide all my icons and then
pa sam sakrio sve svoje ikone i onda
when I need to do something like work
kada moram da radim nešto poput posla
I just unhide them find my thing open it
Samo ih otkrijem da mi otkriju stvar
and then I hide them again okay so it's
i onda ih opet sakrijem, pa je tako
similar
slično
yeah what do you keep on your desktop
Da, šta držiš na radnoj površini
I'm just curious for work like mostly
Samo sam radoznao za posao
just like work programs like the
baš kao i radni programi poput
operating station yes oh yeah exactly
radna stanica da oh točno
okay so make sense and then on my home
U redu, onda ima smisla i onda na mojoj kući
computer it's literally just all VR
kompjuter je bukvalno sve VR
games oh yeah but we we actually have
igre oh da, ali mi zapravo imamo
all of the icons up because they're fun
sve ikone gore jer su zabavne
and Dave will change the the order of
i Dave će promeniti redosled
them to like make a smiley face out of
ih volim napraviti smješko od
the icons you know things like that what
ikone znate stvari kao da je ono što
I tend to do is different from what what
Imam tendenciju da radim drugačije od onoga što
you've what your approach has been in
imate ono što je vaš pristup bio
that I will just create a folder on my
da ću samo napraviti mapu na mom
desktop and that's where I put
desktop i tu sam stavio
everything so that my desktop looks
sve tako da izgleda moj desktop
clean but under the hood there is
čist, ali ispod haube postoji
actually this mess of tiles how do you
zapravo ovaj nered pločica kako ti ide
like what kinds of why that's how I make
kakve su to razloge zbog kojih tako ja pravim
my email look organized many emails and
moj email izgleda organizovano mnogo e-mailova i
then I just have created a folder for
onda sam samo kreirao folder za
every single person who's ever sent me
svaka osoba koja me nikada nije poslao
an email and I'm like wow that goes in
e-mail i ja sam kao wow koji ulazi
the Ravi folder a single filter that
u Ravi folderu jedan filter
moves everything into a different folder
premješta sve u drugu mapu
and it makes my in book inbox look like
i čini da moja ulazna pošta izgleda kao
I do things I am very big on redundancy
Radim stvari koje sam jako velik u redundanciji
so I save copies of copies of copies you
tako da čuvam kopije kopija
use Photoshop so you know what it's like
koristite Photoshop kako biste znali kakav je
to have a PSD file and lose your work
imati PSD datoteku i izgubiti posao
and all those layers that you've spent
i sve one slojeve koje ste potrošili
hours and hours working on to lose that
sati i sati radeći na tome da to izgubimo
PSD and you have a ping but your PSD is
PSD i imate ping ali vaš PSD je
gone and now you're you know what do you
nestala i sada si vi znate šta vam
do so I
uradi to ja
file1 dot PSD file - dot PSD file 3 dot
file1 dot PSD datoteka - točka PSD datoteke 3 točke
PSD so they're all the same thing at
PSD tako da su sve iste stvari na
different iterations of the file with
različite iteracije datoteke sa
various ways of being able to go back in
razni načini da se mogu vratiti
time but I never ever lose more than
ali nikad više ne gubim više od toga
you'd say the one sessions work because
rekli biste da jedna sesija radi jer
I always save as an incremental number
Uvek čuvam kao inkrementalni broj
but then at the end of the day I end up
ali onda na kraju dana završim
with a folder filled with tons and tons
sa fasciklom ispunjenim tonama i tonama
of these redundant files yeah I think
tih redundantnih fajlova da
that's a great system though numbering
to je sjajan sistem iako broji
it like that because I think I mean in
to je tako jer mislim da mislim na to
terms of my organization of folders this
ovo je moja organizacija mape
is something I I don't know maybe I did
nešto što ja ne znam, možda jesam
a number of years of admin work so this
niz godina admin rada tako da je ovo
kind of started me off very early in
Nekako me je počela vrlo rano
terms of folder organization but in
uslovi organizacije direktorijuma, ali u
terms of actually I have the reverse
U stvari, ja imam obrnuto
problem though in terms of anything
problem iako u bilo čemu
graphic design related or graphics
grafički dizajn ili grafika
related nightmare you know five
srodnu noćnu moru znate pet
different you know files name with the
različito znate imena datoteka sa
word final in it right if you're doing
ako je to tačno
graphic design that's or if you're using
grafički dizajn koji je ili ako koristite
those kinds of files so weighty right so
one vrste datoteka koje su tako u pravu
yeah that's I think that's an excellent
Da , mislim da je to odlično
solution probably to add to that I think
rješenje vjerojatno da dodam da mislim
the only thing that can be done if your
jedina stvar koja se može učiniti ako vaš
files are disorganized the way I do it
fajlovi su neorganizovani kao ja
or have done it is to clean it up right
ili ste to uradili je da to očistite
after you finish that particular piece
nakon što završite taj određeni komad
of work because that's when you remember
posla, jer se tada sjećate
which ones are which right and after
koje su tačno i posle
that it's just a nightmare like after
da je to samo noćna mora
that you open it up and it's like like
da ga otvoriš i to je kao
thank you sort by date I can show you my
hvala vam sortiraj po datumu mogu vam pokazati moje
graphic designer actually see how she
grafički dizajner zapravo vidi kako ona
does it's always horrendous okay so this
Da li je to uvek užasno u redu
is the the worst so under the hood folks
je najgore tako ispod ljudi
yeah you're not nearly as bad as me
Da, nisi skoro tako loš kao ja
though that's not well I mean this is
iako to nije dobro, mislim to je
this is because why maybe because I
to je zato što možda zato što ja
haven't done graphic design too much if
nisam previše grafički dizajnirao ako
you look at my old Mac it would be a lot
pogledate moj stari Mac, to bi bilo mnogo
worse yeah
gore da
however
kako god
contrary to everything graphic design my
suprotno svemu što je moj grafički dizajn
other folders are alright so folder
drugi folderi su u redu pa mapa
organization I don't know what's what's
Ne znam šta je
so you have the approach of putting a
tako da imate pristup stavljanja
folder on your desktop I organize
mapu na radnoj površini koju organizujem
everything by date by date so when I
sve po datumu po datumu, kada sam
create a folder it's like today it would
napravite mapu kao danas
be the folder name would be 2018 Oh 704
da je ime mape 2018 Oh 704
- whatever it is that I'm working on I
- šta god da radim na I
do that - yeah so that's that's my
uradite to - da, tako da je to moj
project folders and that's how I do
projektne mape i tako ja radim
everything right so what would you do
sve je u redu, pa šta biste vi uradili
like so I'll just show you what I have
kao da ću vam pokazati šta imam
here so I have these are basically all
evo, tako da ih imam u osnovi sve
my document folders hmm would this look
moji folderi dokumenata hmm bi ovo izgledalo
similar to what you would
slično onome što biste htjeli
oh no mine is much longer I'll show you
O, ne moj je mnogo duže
so basically what I did is these are all
tako da je u osnovi ono što sam uradio jesu sve to
the folders I actually have used since
mape koje sam do sada koristio
last year 2017 and the only thing that
prošle godine 2017. i jedino što
I've altered for this show is the
Sam mijenjati za ovu emisiju je
sensitive Docs I created another and the
osetljivim Dokumentima stvorio sam drugi i
sensitive Doc's really is just actually
osetljivi Doc je zapravo zapravo
any folders that have more personal
bilo koje fascikle koje imaju više ličnih karaktera
things so I literally have one called
stvari, tako da sam ih doslovno nazvao
Docs which is a bit of my miscellaneous
Dokumenti koji su malo moje
folder and then money is anything
pa onda novac je sve
related to money photos of course photos
odnose se na fotografije fotografija kursa
like Facebook photos family photos and
kao i Facebook fotografije porodičnih fotografija i
writing I have you know my folders
pišem da znate moje fascikle
2017-2018 and then I just I name my
2017-2018, a onda sam samo sam ime mog
documents as you do so that even if
dokumente kao što to radite, čak i ako
they're altered later it'll still say
kasnije su izmenjeni i još će reći
2018 - you know 4 - April - 24 or
2018 - znate 4. - 24. april ili
whatever so yeah so I think that's I
šta god da, tako da mislim da je to ja
mean I'll show you some of these folders
mislim da ću vam pokazati neke od ovih mapa
but they're like my classes it looks
ali oni su kao moje klase koje izgleda
incredibly organized to me and and I'm
neverovatno organizovan za mene i ja
interested to hear I know the chat room
zainteresovan da čujem sobu za razgovor
has been has been chatting away I don't
je je razgovor dalje ne znam
know if you've caught much of it and I'm
znam da li ste uhvatili mnogo toga i ja sam
sorry that I you know I'm not really
Žao mi je što ja znam da nisam
monitoring the chat room very well
veoma dobro prati sobu za razgovor
tonight but I think just getting it
večeras, ali mislim da je samo dobila
through through my mind that hey I need
kroz moj um koji mi treba
to be this organized I would love to be
da bih bio ovako organizovan, volela bih da budem
that organized
koji je organizovan
I would also love to be that organizer I
Takođe bih volio da budem taj organizator
appeared that organized from day to day
pojavili su se organizovani iz dana u dan
don't open the one folder on my desktop
ne otvarajte jednu mapu na mom desktopu
order that you can understand though if
redosled koji možete razumeti iako
is if it's within your own language then
ako je to onda na vašem jeziku
do you ever lose ooh what what is no I
da li ikada izgubiš ono što nije
don't lose things because I name things
ne gubite stvari zato što ja imenujem stvari
very verbose Lee so I'm able to do a
veoma verbozan Lee, tako da mogu da uradim
search within filenames I can use find
pretraživanje unutar imena datoteka koje mogu koristiti find
in the Linux terminal and I can find
u Linux terminalu i ja mogu naći
anything that I'm looking for where I
sve što tražim tamo gde ja
run into trouble is my projects
naići na probleme su moji projekti
transcend the folder structure of
transcendira strukturu direktorijuma
documents graphic design video
dokumenti grafički dizajn videa
production because I'm working on things
produkciju jer radim na stvarima
like a logo for a video and things like
kao logo za video i slične stvari
that so it makes it really hard to
da tako da čini zaista teško
organize in that way oh so that's where
organizovati na taj način oh tako da je to gdje
the dating really helps organizing by
datiranje zaista pomaže organizaciju
date okay so when you're looking for
datum u redu tako da kada tražite
files let's say you're looking for a
fajlove, recimo da tražite a
logo for a video project that you did
logo za video projekat koji ste napravili
last month how would you go about so for
prošli mjesec kako bi to uradio
example there's a category-5 folder on
Na primer, tu je mapa kategorije 5
my server and in category 5 is a
moj server iu kategoriji 5 je a
breakdown of every show so technology TV
slom svake emisije tako da tehnologija TV
is this show and within that folder
je ova emisija i unutar te mape
there's graphics backgrounds animated
postoje animirane grafičke pozadine
backgrounds and things like that video
pozadine i tako video stvari
assets and then they're organized by
i onda su organizovani od strane
seasons so season 4 is different from
sezona se razlikuje od sezone 4
season 7 from season 11 right of course
sezona 7 od sezone 11 desno naravno
and so I can always find what I'm
i tako uvijek mogu naći ono što sam
looking for that way but then I do end
tražim taj način, ali onda završavam
up with a lot of old stuff well it's
sa mnogo starih stvari i to je
really good that you're not like hey
stvarno dobro da nisi kao hej
Sasha do you want to organize my stuff
Saša hoćeš da organizuješ moje stvari
for me oh I would literally just have
za mene oh bih bukvalno samo imao
one folder and it would be like I
jedna fascikla i to bi bilo kao ja
wouldn't think to subcategorize buy
ne bi pomislio da podkategorizira kupnju
anything we just all be in there with
sve sa čime smo svi zajedno
the assumption that I could go into
pod pretpostavkom da sam mogao ući u
there and then click the search bar and
zatim kliknite na traku za pretraživanje i
then just search light at random some
onda samo svjetiljkom nasumce neke
words that I know are part of that like
reči koje znam su deo toga
like fork that makes broccoli tastes
kao viljuška koja pravi ukus brokule
like chocolate like I feel like I would
kao čokolada kao što sam se kao da bih
search she actually has that document
ona zapravo ima taj dokument
right that's the this is right on the
To je tačno
top I'm sure it's sorted by priority it
vrh Siguran sam da je sortiran po prioritetu
says 1 1 chocolate tasting broccoli
kaže 1 1 čokoladna brokula
exactly I'd be interested to know what
tačno bih bio zainteresovan da znam šta
our community thinks and what our
naša zajednica misli i šta je naša
community is is doing to keep files
zajednica radi da čuva datoteke
organized
organizovan
maybe something she's shared with us has
možda nešto što je podijelila s nama
inspired you to do things a little bit
inspirisao vas da malo uradite stvari
differently maybe in in work or at home
drugačije možda u poslu ili kod kuće
and we'd love to hear from you if you
i voleli bismo da čujemo od vas
could comment below if you're watching
mogu da komentarišu ispod ako gledate
this on Facebook on Facebook YouTube
ovo na Facebook-u na Facebook-u YouTube
wherever you are or if you're watching
gde god da ste ili ako gledate
this on cable TV make sure you get on to
ovo na kablovskoj televiziji pazite na to
our website category-five TV and click
naš sajt website -pet TV i klikni
on contact us and we'll be sure to share
kontaktirajte nas i mi ćemo biti sigurni da ćemo to podijeliti
your story with shizue and the rest of
svoju priču sa sizuom i ostatkom
the community as well anything any final
zajednice kao i sve konačne
thoughts that before because I don't
misli prije nego što ja ne
want to cut you off
želim da te isečem
oh okay so final thoughts final thoughts
oh, u redu, konačne misli konačne misli
folks can you tell the t-shirt story
ljudi mogu reći priču o majici
sure so when I clean up of my space so
siguran kad sam očisti od mojih prostora tako
this is back to the book the
ovo se vraća u knjigu
life-changing magic of tidying up when I
čaroliju koja mijenja život kada se sređujem
was cleaning on my space the ideas you
čistio sam vaše ideje
hold on to everything that is magic and
držite se svega što je magično i
joyful and just you is like brilliant to
veseo i samo ti je kao sjajan u
you and I came across this t-shirt which
ti i ja smo naišli na ovu majicu koja
is a t-shirt I wear at night and it's so
je majica koju nosim noću i tako je
comfy you've had that a while yeah I've
udoban ste imali to neko vrijeme da sam
had it it's a threadbare yeah I bought
da je to bio izlizan da sam kupio
it I think at Lara in Japan and like two
mislim na Laru u Japanu i na dva
or something so it's like 2008 and it's
ili nešto tako, to je kao 2008. i to je
like my favorite shirt ever like it's
kao moja omiljena košulja ikada kao da je
just the way it feels when I wear it so
baš onako kako misli kad sam ga nositi tako
I wear it at night and I actually
Nosim ga noću i zapravo
because it didn't look good like it's a
jer nije dobro izgledati kao da je to
little fit it's faded by Nature right
Malo se uklapa to je izbledelo pravo iz prirode
and it's a little bit more a tiny bit
i malo je malo
more faded now but I think it's actually
sada više blijedi, ali mislim da je to zapravo
supposed to be this thing it's it's back
trebalo bi da bude ovo što se vratilo
in now but basically the idea is that
sada, ali u osnovi je ideja
this shirt I actually threw out with my
ovu košulju sam stvarno izbacio sa mojom
bags of stuff because it didn't look
vreće stvari jer to nije izgledalo
good and I was like I cried I actually
dobro i bio sam kao da sam plakao
literally cried and this was a hard
bukvalno je plakao i to je bilo teško
thing to let go of
stvar koju treba pustiti
but that's our old mindset of wanting to
ali to je naš stari način razmišljanja koji žele da
get rid of stuff to declutter yeah and
riješi stvari na declutter da i
it hurts yeah it hurts it hurt and does
Boli me da ga boli to boli i da li
not hurt when I throw away my fat shirts
ne boli kad bacim svoje debele košulje
every object has a different spirit to
svaki predmet ima drugačiji duh
it I'm telling you I have a guitar and I
Kažem ti da imam gitaru i ja
literally I belted it in on my way over
bukvalno sam ga zakačio na svom putu
here oh yeah yeah I had to I know it's
ovdje da, da, morao sam znati da je
weird but I can't
čudno, ali ne mogu
but that thing is beautiful so this
ali ta stvar je tako lepa
shirt I threw out but I sneakily
košulju sam izbacio, ali sam se ušuljao
actually took it back because I liked it
zapravo su ga, jer sam se sviđa
that much and I hadn't actually gotten
toliko i nisam zapravo dobila
to the portion of the book where Marie
na dio knjige u kojoj je Marie
Kondo says oh it's cool to keep like one
Kondo kaže da je kul ostati kao jedan
or two things that are you know on the
ili dvije stvari koje su vam je poznato na
sly things that you really like like a
lukavim stvarima koje zaista volite
pajama shirt and I was like cool she
pidžama majica i ja sam bila cool
gave me the thumbs up
dao mi je palac gore
I could probably speak more on the whole
Verovatno bih mogao više da govorim uopšte
on the open portal that that actually
na otvorenom portalu da je to zapravo
created with regards to this
stvorena u vezi sa ovim
organization and messiness and
organizacije i nereda i
prioritization and the idea that having
prioriteta i ideju da ima
a messy room is actually in some times
neuredna soba je zapravo u nekim vremenima
and circumstances the better thing to do
i okolnosti, to je bolje
in my opinion but I'm not a famous super
po mom mišljenju, ali ja nisam poznati super
step what my authority is based on but
korak na kojem se temelji moj autoritet, ali
for those of you who are interested in
za one koji vas zanimaju
finding out more about being
saznati više o tome
disorganized and what that relates to
neorganizovan i na šta se to odnosi
Robbie was exactly right it is to do
Robbie je bio u pravu što treba da uradi
with creativity intelligence it's also
sa kreativnom inteligencijom to je takođe
to do with being a Bri Kohler we'll talk
s obzirom da smo Bri Kohler, razgovarat ćemo
about the anthropologist Claude
o antropologu Claudeu
levi-strauss
levi-strauss
anyway all sorts of great things but
u svakom slučaju sve vrste velikih stvari, ali
please do Google search that because
molim vas da pretražite Google zato što
that actually changed my perspective on
to je zapravo promijenilo moju perspektivu
things and that's the asterisks that is
stvari i to su zvezdice
a little bit of a mystery just a Google
malo misterije samo Google
search away there you go and we still
pretražite tamo idete i mi još
have the book in our shop as well cat5
imate knjigu u našoj radnji kao i cat5
dot TV slash tidy how has that just as a
dot TV slash uredan kako je to samo kao
final thought how has that mindset of
konačna misao kako je to razmišljanje
holding on to something that you
držeći se za nešto što ti
otherwise would have discarded how is
inače bi odbacili kako je
that transcended to your MacBook and
koje su prevazišle vaš MacBook i
your organization technologically have
vaša organizacija je tehnološki
there been any of those files that you
Bilo je onih fajlova koje ste vi
might have removed but have held on to
možda je uklonjen, ali je zadržan
well this is the miracle of technology
ovo je čudo tehnologije
you can actually be a little more
zapravo možeš biti malo više
infinite with what you have you're not
beskrajno sa onim što imaš
limited to the same amount of confined
ograničena na istu količinu ograničenih
space yeah I mean you can keep all of
Mislim da možete zadržati sve
those shows on your computer and it's
te emisije na računaru i to je
not like a heavy load unless you can't
ne kao težak teret, osim ako ne možete
find it which is another you imagine I
pronađi ono što si drugi zamislio
just it just don't dawned on me like
samo mi se nije svidelo
every single Netflix show will
svaki prikaz Netflixa će
but on a VHS like could you imagine if
ali na VHS-u kao što možete zamisliti ako
you had that whole library or catalog of
Imali ste čitavu biblioteku ili katalog
things you can watch but as things that
stvari koje možete gledati, ali kao stvari
would be horrid on a single VHS like I
bilo bi strašno na jednom VHS-u kao što sam ja
know I'm talking about like if
znam da pričam kao da
metaphorical being you had VHS tapes for
Metaforično je da ste imali VHS trake
every show right right but now we don't
svako pravo pokazuje, ali sada ne
have that we're like yes yeah we're
da smo mi kao da da
minimalists really now as far as I get
minimalisti stvarno sada koliko ja mogu
all on a computer and you don't have to
sve na kompjuteru i ne morate
have you know bookcases full of VHS yeah
da li ste znali da su pune VHS da
my phone can have thousands upon
moj telefon može imati na hiljade
thousands of full-length CDs on it yeah
hiljade CD-ova na njemu
yes and I think that's the I mean it
da i mislim da je to ono što mislim
sounds a bit messianic it starts but the
zvuči pomalo mesijanski počinje već
horrendous words were but I mean
strašne reči su bile, ali mislim
technology really has this capability of
tehnologija zaista ima tu sposobnost
allowing us to stay organized focus but
omogućujući nam da ostanemo organizirani fokus, ali
also to allow us to like allow our
takođe da nam dozvolite da dopustimo naše
creativity to flourish right and and if
kreativnost da procvate kako treba i ako
that means the manifestation of that is
to znači da je manifestacija koja je
the like a trillion files which can be
kao trilion fajlova koji mogu biti
organized in certain ways then that's
organizovani na određeni način
what it is but that's the amazing part
šta je to, ali to je neverovatan deo
about it
o tome
so that would be my application is
to bi bila moja prijava
creativity away on on your computers and
kreativnost na vašim kompjuterima i
so that brings us back to kind of the
tako da nas vraća na vrstu
technology TV and of things where I need
Tehnologija TV i stvari tamo gdje mi je potrebno
to say make sure you backup your files
da budete sigurni da ste napravili rezervne kopije datoteka
folks yes make sure you've got a backup
ljudi da budite sigurni da imate podršku
because I'd hate to see you lose that
jer ne bih voleo da to izgubiš
millions and trillions of files that
milijunima i trilionima fajlova
Shizue has just given you permission to
Shizue ti je upravo dao dozvolu
have on that no can I do a 17-second
na to ne mogu da uradim 17 sekundi
absolutely okay because speaking of
apsolutno u redu jer govorim o tome
creativity I have a little video and
kreativnost Imam mali video i
it's literally 17 seconds all right
to je doslovno 17 sekundi u redu
folks
ljudi
slow rap making it easier to wrongful
polagan rap što olakšava nezakonitost
and other two-syllable in the nick of
i druga dva sloga u nadimku
time reppin real fast makes it how to
vreme reppin stvarno brzo čini kako
understand google search another lyrics
razumeti google pretragu drugih tekstova
and disservice to your fans slow alright
i lošu uslugu svojim fanovima spor u redu
we can't hear here in the studio very
ne čujemo ovde u studiju
cool
cool
alright well thank you she zoo for for
U redu, hvala ti za zoo
sharing with us tonight do check out the
deliti sa nama večeras i pogledati
book by Mary condo the life-changing
knjiga Marije Condo koja menja život
magic of tidying up a cat5 TV slash tidy
čarolija sređivanja cat5 TV slash
it really is a game changer and I know
to je zaista izmjenjivač i znam
it sounds kind of silly
zvuči nekako blesavo
it's a tidying kind of thing but it
to je uredna vrsta stvari ali to
really works well when your space feels
stvarno dobro radi kada se vaš prostor osjeća
good to you like if it's not
dobro ti se sviđa ako nije
overwhelming to walk into your home
neodoljiv da uđete u vaš dom
because all of a sudden you're looking
jer odjednom tražite
around and it's just simple it's all the
i samo je jednostavno sve
things that you like and it's organized
stvari koje volite i organizovane su
it's like your brain can relax when you
kao da se tvoj mozak može opustiti kada ti
get home and then life gets better
vrati se kući i onda se život popravi
[Music]
[Music] \ t
[Applause]
[Aplauz]
you
vas
[Music]
[Music] \ t